you're american i'm american with just
him
lyrics can we just be all americans
yeah we are we all americans but we live
in two different americas
that's what it is people forget that
and i don't think everybody that doesn't
understand what we go through
is necessarily racist or bigoted that's
a far jump it's a lot of folks that just
straight up don't know what it's like
you got to educate them you got to
educate them on the kind of america
you live in i'd go to best buy and give
a dude some straightening
straighten his ass out i'm straightening
do the best by going to decide i don't
need a bag with my purchase
you just have an iphone case i figured
you could just pop that opener you know
i ain't popping you
put it in the bag and you got
in a bag what do you need a bag for i
understand where you need a bag it's
wasteful
recycle don't you care about the earth
i go sir this has nothing to do with the
earth
i'm a black man in america
i gotta leave this store with a bag bruh
it's about safety
i'm black i don't get the luxury of just
walking out with in my hand that
is a roll of the dice that is a
horrifying day if i don't know
not only do i need that bag i need
that receipt
and staple it to the outside
i don't want a receipt in my hand you
staple my receipt to the outside like
chinese carryout
and i hold it up in the air a lion king
hakuna matata an iphone case
out of best buy for me in my stand up if
i haven't made you uncomfortable
somewhere in there then i don't think
i've done my job
and i'm not there to make you smile and
feel but
this is gonna be a real conversation
about stuff that's happening in the
world now that might be a couple
goofy-ass jokes
somewhere in that performance but
somewhere in there there needs to be
something
that speaks to an honest observation
about the world and i don't think every
comedian sets out
to change the world and politics and
blackness but even if it's just about
relationships it's still your truth
you've experienced something and you're
reporting it back to the people
and to me that is the type of comedy
that will always fly the
the furthest and the highest
is comedy that is a reflection of the
human condition
[Music]
the role of black comedy with what's
happening in the
world today is no different than
the role of black comedy from the
beginning
it's all about telling the real story
from our perspective what better place
to be able to tell
your story than on a stand-up stage
with freedom of speech and letting it
just
go that's a comic i've been there before
right well i needed to go to the club
so if something crazy happened in the
news where i was like yo i don't know
how to deal with this
my i for me right away i'm going to the
comedy club
and i don't care if it's just for me to
do a set or or i'm coming there just to
watch
some other cats do their thing because i
need the laugh red fox
set it to a malcolm x you got to do
something to get people excited and
engaged
and a sense of humor is the best thing
where everybody can meet
at one place you can laugh people into
some truth and you can hit them with
some realities of what's going on in the
world
sometimes i like to have fun and it's
all fun and then sometimes it's
like
you know what this is the up
that's going on in the world
and a lot of times when you're a black
comic and you're and i'm
mainstream comedy sometimes white people
don't want to hear that
you know or they want they tune in when
it feels comfortable for them
comedy especially in the black community
truth to power
i always say we're the third eye we're
right below
the pastor it's jesus
it's your clergy then it's comedians
i'm not preaching i'm a stand-up comic
my first
uh priority is to entertain you if i'm
making you laugh
and i'm educating you at the same time
brilliant
so i talk about police brutality in my
set but i do it in a way you don't even
realize i'm talking about
police brutality and then you go oh
i don't care about starbucks banning
wifi for porn that doesn't interest me
that's for white dudes
you know it's white dudes black guys get
arrested just for not buying coffee
can you imagine if they got their dicks
out
i shut the penis the penis was resistant
we have always from the richard prize
the dick gregory god rest assault
made society see what they was doing to
us
in a comical way and just laugh about it
to keep from crying about it
or being valid about it so i take that
on
i take on that responsibility very
serious
i have to talk to my people and say yeah
this happened to me too
i hate to see any baseball player having
troubles because that's a great sport
for my people
that is the only sport in the world
where negro can shake a stick at a white
man and won't start no ride
dick gregory represented us
not just as a stand-up comedian but
as a civil rights activist
dick gregory spoke when i was a freshman
in college the way he schooled me
medgar evers schooled him and it was all
about
doing the right thing for all and not
one
great men have said before that
[Music]
a soldier can fight for his country
against another country
but it takes something like a super
special man to fight his country when it
is wrong
if you're a black entertainer and you
talk about race it's you're going to
take a hit like it's just natural
because there's always going to be
backlash same thing with like kaepernick
like white people don't want to see you
talking about
the issues they just want to laugh
you're just a comedian just stick to
your jad
i feel more connected to artists that
use their platform especially if you get
the opportunity to be in white rooms on
white television in front of white
people
especially white people that generally
don't see you you should be talking
about the issues but at the same time
you need to stay funny and i think
that's
what separates a great like dick gregory
as he was able to be political and still
funny because at the end of the day
people want to laugh
you can always laugh at problems that's
right
everyone in the whole world know this is
a wrong
so then you can make humor out of this
and matter like you enlightening people
on just what's going on it's like one of
the last
bastions of free speech that we have is
true comedy
you know we used to have the last poets
you know nikki giovanni and we don't
have poets anymore that are famous
poets that can speak for us you know
this revolution will not be televised
and all that we don't have anybody
holding our footsteps the only people we
have left
is comics we won't be censored we don't
give a
tawanda page had a lot to say that
people don't realize martial warfield i
really like watching the news though
cause on the news they have their own
language
it's almost like they're talking in code
see they even have a code word for black
people on the news
it's youth uh 35 year old detroit youth
was today shot and killed by a 14 year
old utah man
think about it think about it something
that comes uh readily to mind the cover
of bicentennial
has prior uh in a chain
of different fires right in different
forms he's a boxer he's a preacher
he's a businessman right and the figure
holding the chain is
uncle sam to the corner and so that had
itself physically
back in the day when album covers were
also
part of the humor so already performing
a definite critique
of the celebration of america in its
bicentennial
and the persistence of enslavement
in different forms uh in 1976.
richard pryor is easily the best job to
do it richard pryor had a line
you go to jail looking for justice and
all you find is just us
no white person can absorb that the same
as a black person like a black person
it's like
yes thank you for satan exactly
it's a moment of truth for black people
it's a moment of realization for white
people who are getting for the first
time a lot of them for the first time
to see the world through a black man's
eyes police got a chokehold they use out
here though man they choke did
that
that mean you'd be dead when they
through right did you know that
wait nigga's going yeah we need a wife
of noah i have no idea
yeah if you grab your legs one grab your
head it'll snap oh he broke
can you break a is it okay let's
check the minnow yep
you can bring a right there see
let's drag him down
okay it's the window into black life
black opinions black thoughts you know
you look at somebody like chris rock
and some of the brilliant he said
white people wouldn't even understand
some of this
at least politically if he didn't say it
the white man thinks he's losing the
country affirmative action
and illegal aliens and we're
losing the country
lucy shut the up white people ain't
losing
if y'all losing who's winning then you
got a guy like kat williams who i
i don't think cat will ever get the
credit he deserves being as smart as he
is
he says something back in the pimp
chronicles part one
that i wrote a um thematic essay on and
i got an
a on it because he said something about
the war you don't believe we gangsters
tell me what the iraqi uniform look like
don't worry i'll wait cause you ain't
never seen that we ain't
killing that army we killing them
we over there killing in
sweatpants tank tops
flip-flops and a cowboy hat you
shouldn't have been talking
then i thought about it i was like i
don't know what that uniform looks like
so he's right we really are killing
people and we don't care
because they don't classify them as
people they classify them as insurgents
that's brilliant i'm gonna be honest
with you white guys you guys are it
don't nobody trust y'all now don't
nobody trust
you and it used to be like the crazy
looking white dude nobody trusts
uh a white in khakis i'm getting
the out do you hear me
if he looks like he manages the arby's i
got to go
what is what is he doing here
no i never adjust which is why it's
taking me 17 years to make it
you're like oh where you been i've been
here just
trying to figure out my life i go on
stage and i that's what i deal with like
whatever i'm going through
whatever is going on in the world i deal
with it
because sometimes i'm nonsense it's fine
but i want to say something you know and
that doesn't mean that i always
hit the mark it just means that i'm i
want to say something and i want to make
sure that i make a
great impact and my responsibility
is maybe sometimes to my detriment is to
always push this narrative that if we
still don't have it easy as black people
and not that we want it easy but we
should just at least have some form of
rest i should be able to wake up
and be like oh i'm going to live my day
as yamaneika not having experience as i
go through the world where it's like up
somebody doing some cause i'm black
or this i'm being treated this way
because i'm black
or i'm a woman sometimes you can feel
um powerless and
comedy for me is the thing that makes me
feel powerful
when we do go out to see comedy we seek
it
we go out and we seek it i need to laugh
you know because something's going on i
got one bit about um
we always talk about white male
privilege in this country but we never
talk about white female privilege which
i think is a
lot more privileged when i hit that
beginning part
and i say that you'll see some of the
looks going
what what what privilege then when i
break it down i get to one of my first
bits in that joke
i wish i could be as comfortable around
the police as drunk white women
and i start breaking it down about
things i see them get away with versus
what we can get away with
and this is a true story i've seen a
white girl pissing between the cars and
this officer was being
so patient with her ma'am could you
ma'am when you're done
ma'am cuz you plea and she turned up
looked at him and said get out of my
face you pig
and it was a part of me just looking at
that it's like word
you tell em you pig but then it
was a
bigger part of me knowing that i
couldn't get away with that the kind
wanted to see the officer taser just a
little bit
because you need to know it's real out
here i couldn't get away with half of
that
meanwhile he's calling you ma'am miss
and all that i've been called for
not turning around fast enough to talk
to the cops
so you know sometimes they have the
adverse reaction but
if it's a good joke they'll take it as
long as you get to a good punchline
they'll laugh at it at the end eating
and breathing have become unexpectedly
dangerous
in my life i'm actually going to stop
calling my allergies that that's a wimpy
name for something that might kill you
out of nowhere
so i'm now going to call my allergies my
police exactly because they might erase
my existence
and people will react the same way why'd
you go outside that day you guys know
what i mean exact same
disregard for human life okay some of
you with me
some of you feel weird about race and
that's fine because that's how i woke up
this morning and every single morning
i've woken up just what black again hope
i make it
the police are out and it's already
skinned 30.
i'm a contestant on will this get me
killed anyway guys um
come with me or not when i moved from
atlanta to indianapolis there was no
urban
scene so it kind of forced me into the
mainstream circuit
so i would tell these stories and people
would be blown away and how i was raised
you know the type of parents i had the
environment that i came
from that's what they're learning when
they come to my show like hey
you want to close your door and act like
people like me don't exist but it does
i'm 16 years old i got two kids two and
one years old
and i'm living in a hood in atlanta and
in this hood i'm you know i'm trying to
survive so i
go out and start me a small business
well i was selling crack but we're gonna
call it a small business tonight
okay white people
i always had to keep a client in the car
with me because i was 16 years old with
a learner's permit and i didn't want to
risk the chance of losing my
permit
i think it's an eye opener when i'm
standing on stage talking about my life
so honestly
and i'm a girl you really don't hear
girls say
they traffic cocaine they've been shot
and i have this little saying when i say
hold my hand white woman i'm about to
take you to the hood
you let it go they gonna get your ass
and i just walk them through all these
crazy stories in my life
and i bring them back at the end in the
comedy club and sell them in their seats
oh um i just wrote it uh yesterday
um i was at a hawks game just today
because you know i must have been bored
if i go to a hawks game
and i bought the ticket i was in the
concession stand
and i had a friend beside me and i said
damn
the hawks are really whooping some ass
today they beating the knicks
and it was a young lady beside me a
sister
i said i'm sorry for using that language
in your present using ass
excuse please forgive me and uh she said
no it's cool
i'm just you know it didn't offend me
it's just i was just worried my mother
didn't need to hear this
she's 82 years old she don't need to
hear
you know that kind of language i said
well she's 82 years old
she didn't heard words worse than ass
not my mother i said yes she is 82 like
what
like get off my porch
you want to vote recite all the
ingredients that's in shampoo
give me the national anthem backwoods
and then read it to me forward and tell
me the 54th word in the national anthem
your mother didn't heard some worst
if she's 82 years old then
ass she said not my mother she lived up
north i said it was everywhere
and that was my point i used to do this
bit
about the first slave that ever had to
read right and the whole process
of this i was thinking to myself i'm
like
we don't appreciate or talk about
enough the legacy of the people that
survived so that we could be here right
all the slaves that made it and didn't
die and you know just went
through the whole process so many times
people were telling you like let's
forget that let's not talk about it
slavery's over
we're done with that i'm like but what
what about those unsung heroes
that we don't really have documentation
on because nobody was writing
the stories down and most of the stories
that did come from that
were from a white perspective of what
was going on
and i said how hilarious that must be
to be like the first black person that
was like sent up north to read and then
you try to
you're so proud of all the
accomplishments that you made and that
you made it up north
and now you want to do is write a letter
and you want to send it back to them
but you got to send it to master's
mailbox because then aren't a
mailbox
and then he like what the is it who
the
who getting littered around you know
it's like this whole this whole world
and so at first when i
just i said nobody wants to hear that
right
and then as i went into it and people
started to laugh i go oh
how crazy can i make this world what
what can i say and it just starts to add
layers
i mean that's my process i don't know
how other people's process
some people's process is i just want
people to like me
when i go on stage and i don't think
like that
i just want people to hear what i'm
saying and
like it but um i went to a psychiatrist
and for those of you like i'm happy and
what's that it's like
shut the up um no you go to a
person you tell them all the deep dark
secrets you can't tell your friends they
throw pills at you and some days you
feel all right
a lot of my first jokes and half my
material now
is sad things that happened to me or
things that bothered me or something
someone said to me that made me feel bad
and then i made that into a joke i've
gotten to like sort of exercise a lot of
things that
i a lot of issues i had with being a kid
a lot of issues i have being a black
woman
and it's just because if you're as a
black person a person any person of
color
you're just you're going to experience
more trauma
and that's just an amazing way to deal
with that is to be like
like this thing hurt me like i talk
about depression for example
that's not fun it's not fun for me to go
through that but when i talk about it on
stage i feel better
i feel seen it's not as scary
embarrassing thing about me anymore
because i'm telling you and i'm changing
the narrative
with my jokes first question he asked me
pretty early was like do you have a
boyfriend girlfriend a relationship i
was like yeah
he was like do you love him and i was
like
what did he say i don't say it first he
didn't think that was amusing uh
he's also taken back he's like that's a
little inappropriate given the setting
and i was like
but doctor all the worlds will stay okay
inappropriate
it was like um do you do drugs and i was
like
it's inappropriate i'm goodness yep yep
yep yep i paid a lot of money
um towards the end though he got really
serious we were having a good time
and then he was like you suffer from
suicidal thoughts
and i was like yeah like honestly like
that's a big part of why i came
i have those thoughts but whenever i
think about what it would do to my
friends and family
it makes it something that's impossible
to go through with and this man looked
at me and then looked at his notepad and
he's like
not if you're determined what
but now i kill myself so bad
i have a best friend name is mike
machokey and um i was speaking to him
one day
and i was like oh yeah you know i'm
about to finish college i'm i'm doing my
thing and he's like man
you got to get on stage man you're funny
like we had you hosting the vents back
in college you gotta go on stage i'm
like alright yeah i'm gonna go and say
i'm gonna do it i knew i was gonna do it
then about a week later
he and his fiancee got murdered when
coming home from their uh
from their engagement party losing them
was something that still like
haunts me it it it has me depressed it
there's things that i go through just
like losing some losing two people like
so suddenly right
now i'm able to talk about it on stage
but when i talk about it i make sure
like i like i kind of quote bullying
myself because i'm like all right
you could talk about depression but
don't you be that sadness on stage
you still gotta be funny when i talk
about depression on stage like when i'm
getting into it
it's like the best feeling in the world
because like i see audiences
like i see the response especially like
if i'm doing an all-black show i'll see
a response of like
people laughing and then there's other
people who just like laughing and
looking at me like yeah you know what
i'm like they get it
it's it's not just a joke
to them it's real and it's just a good
bonding experience because
i think that black audiences when they
see me do that they're like you know
what yeah we can
that this is good to talk about we can
talk about it yeah
i don't like walking up behind white
women at night
makes me really uncomfortable
so i cross the street
if i was a white woman i would rob black
dudes
[Laughter]
i walk up to black guys and be like hi
my name is sarah give me your wallet
sarah that's my grandma name give me
your wallet or i'm going to scream about
the
hit here sarah
look at some of the white women like wow
we could actually do that
[Laughter]
so one night i was walking up the block
and this white woman was in front of me
so i went across the street
and then when i got across the street
there was another white woman there so
my only option was
to walk in the middle of the street and
you know i didn't uh and i was just like
you know what this
what's so sad about the whole feeling is
that i don't want to
make her uncomfortable when you know
if you break it down that's her problem
because i'm just trying to get home just
like you and society has
painted this wicked picture of us
we're not given the benefit of doubt
from that i wound up talking about it on
stage and i turned it into a joke
black people react to it was like you
damn right that's right
you know and it's the dudes normally
like yo that's what shut
yeah and white audiences are a little
taken aback at first and then they jump
on it and it's like oh my god i
can't deny this like this is his factual
feelings and truth of what he does we
all have a mission statement
in this uh big movie called life
number one to alleviate pressure
you know and these times we we're under
a lot of pressure that's
comedy's got we gotta alleviate the
pressure that people are under
then we gotta educate because the news
is so slanted and propaganda right now
we have to now educate ourselves so that
we can educate through our humor
what's really going on out here i firmly
firmly believe that all the best
philosophers through the generations
just stopped
majoring in philosophy and just became
comics you know
like the most brilliant people you talk
to make you laugh about whatever it is
that they're talking about because if
you're laughing at it not only do you
not have to
let it be as uh as serious of an idea
but you also just
you understand it better to me being a
black comedian in america means
you got to stand up for something you
got to say something in your material
that's i mean our greatest
i guess comedian that everybody talks
about richie pryor
he said something dick gregory said
something
like say something because that's what
we come from in our material
our kings they said something they made
points they pointed out injustices
and made fun of it say something
you